William Henry Jackson Photochroms
William Henry Jackson Photochroms
circa 1895-1908
Jackson, William Henry, 1843-1942
0.25 linear ft. (88 items)
Photographs taken by the American landscape photographer, of various locations in the American West and Southwest.
4595760
Biographical History
William Henry Jackson (1843-1942) was an American painter, photographer and explorer. Although he ran a portrait studio for a time, he was more interested in the natural landscape, and became known for his photographs of the American West. His photographs were the first ever published of the Yellowstone area, and contributed to its recognition as a national park. [Adapted from J. Paul Getty Museum's page on Jackson.]
The Photochrom process, a type of chromolithography developed in Switzerland, was a labor-intensive method of turning black-and-white photographs in to color prints, notable for their depth and richness. It was licensed in America by the Detroit Photographic Company in the 1890s, of which company Jackson became a partner.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William Henry Jackson Photochroms consists of eighty-eight Photochroms (chromolithographs) taken by American landscape photographer William Henry Jackson. Many are of areas in Colorado, including Cheyenne Mountain and Mount Manitou; others are of California, New Mexico, the Niagara Falls/Thousand Islands area, and Mexico.
The inventory below was provided by the donor, and for the most part reproduces information appearing on the item itself. Information in square brackets was added by staff during processing. "Birth of a Century" plate numbers refer to The Birth of a Century: Early Color Photographs of America, a collection of Jackson's images published in 1999 by I. B. Tauris & Company. Images are listed in the inventory by topic, but are arranged in the box first by size and within that by image number.
Arrangement of the Collection
Although listed in the inventory by topic, the items are arranged in the box first by size and within that by image number.
Related Material
A copy of The Birth of a Century: Early Color Photographs of America, a collection of Jackson's images published in 1999 by I. B. Tauris & Company, is available in general collections; please refer to to locate this item.
Subject and Genre Headings
Photography; Jackson, William Henry, 1843-1942.; Landscape photography -- West (U.S.); Outdoor photography.; Photographers -- 19th century -- United States.; California -- Pictorial works.; Colorado -- Pictorial works.; Mexico -- Pictorial works.; New Mexico -- Pictorial works.; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works.; Photochroms.; Photographs.; Photographer.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Gloves must be work when working with the photographs.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Caroline M. Baillon, 2015.
Appraisal Information
See files.
Inventory
- Photographs
  - Colorado
    - Image #2 Rios los Animos Ca単on [Colorado?], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #6 Cheyenne Mountain [Colorado], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #10 Balanced Rock, Garden of the Gods, 1908 [Colorado], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #14 Lake San Cristobal, 1898 [Colorado], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #16 Birth of a century: Plate 34 Mount of the Holy Cross [Colorado], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #23 Ute Pass [Colorado], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #30 The Old Roadmaster, Clear Creek Ca単on [Colorado], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #51001 Cheyenne Mountain, Colorado, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51002 Pike's Peak from near Colorado City, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51007 Manitou, Colorado, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51017 Ouray [Colorado], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51018 Ouray and Silverton toll road [Colorado], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51019 Rockie Mountain "Canaries" [Colorado], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51023 Currecanti Needle, Black Ca単on, Colorado, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51025 Needle Mountains, Colorado, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51027 Dome Rock, Platte Ca単on, Colorado, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51028 Snowy Range from Bellevue, Colorado, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51042 Birth of a century: Plate 58a, Colorado, Aspen silver mines, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51043 Colorado, "American-Netti" mine, Ouray, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51044 Colorado, placer mining, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51047 Colorado, miner's cabin in winter, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51049 Birth of a century: Plate 60 Colorado, dug out cabins, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51050 Colorado, a pioneer merchant, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51051 Colorado, burros at silver mine, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51054 Colorado, pack train on mountain road, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51055 Birth of a century: Plate 59a Colorado, burros loaded with lumber, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51061 Colorado, The roundup, roping a steer, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51063 Colorado, Mt. Sopris from Spring Gulch Mine, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51073 Fishing on Williams Fork, Middle Fork, Colorado, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #53103 Royal Gorge, Colorado, 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53130 Colorado, the Sangre de Cristo from Poncha Pass, 1898, 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53136 Mount of the Holy Cross [Colorado], 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53151 Birth of a century: Plate 22 Silverton & Sultan Mountain, Colorado, 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53153 Long's Peak from Mont Alto, Colorado 1901, 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53205 Bluffs of the Green River, 1898 [Colorado], 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #[none; donor lists as 14142] Mount of the Holy Cross in the clouds [Colorado], 7x9 (Box 1)
  - New York
    - Image #41 American Fall from Goat Island, Niagara [New York], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #45 Horseshoe Fall, Niagara [New York], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #49 Whirlpool Rapids, Niagara [New York], 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #51104 The rapids above the falls, Niagara [New York], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51109 The Horseshoe Fall, Niagara [New York], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51356 Palisades Rift, Thousand Islands, 1901 [New York], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
  - California
    - Image #51144 California, Mirror Lake, Yosemite Valley, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51170 California, palms at Glen Annie, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51202 West Side Park, Los Angeles [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51221 Yucca cactus at Hesperia, California, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51265 Ramona's Marriage Place, San Diego Cal [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51266 The Lodge, Golden Gate Park, San Francisco, Cal [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51312 Lake Merritt, Oakland, California, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51313 Alligator Head, La Jolla [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51316 The Country Club, Pasadena [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51335 Main entrance & driveway, Leland Stanford Junior University [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51337 Western entrance to inner quadrangle, Leland Stanford Junior University [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51338 Encina Hall, Leland Stanford Junior University [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51370 Grape fruit 1902 [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51398 The Golden Gate, San Francisco 1901 [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51399 Seal Rocks, 1901 [California], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #53006 Lick Observatory, Mt. Hamilton, Cal. 1902 [California], 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53026 Mission Santa Inez 1898 [California], 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53074 Birth of a century: Plate 105, Castle Crags from near Castella, California, 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53077 Birth of a century: Plate 98b Farnsworth's Loop, Santa Catalina Island [California], 7x9 (Box 1)
    - Image #53089 California poppies, 1899, 7x9 (Box 1)
  - Mexico
    - Image #51147 The altar, Church of Guadelupe, City of Mexico, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51148 Lavanderas, City of Mexico, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51149 Canal de la Viga, City of Mexico, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51150 Aztec calendar stone, City of Mexico, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51151 Aztec sacrifical stone, City of Mexico, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51152 Mexico, an Aztec idol, Teoyaomiqui, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51154 Mexican carrete, Chihuahua, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51155 Mexico portales of market, Aguas Calientes, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51162 Mexico, a pulque shop, Tacubaya, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51165 A Mexican hacienda, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51166 Mexico, Falls of Juanacatlan, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
  - New Mexico
    - Image #51236 Relics of an ancient race, Pueblo of San Juan, N.M. [New Mexico], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51285 Going to the spring, Pueblo of San Juan, N.M. [New Mexico], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51286 An "estufa", Pueblo of Taos, N.M. [New Mexico], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51287 Packing wood, Santa Fe, N.M. [New Mexico], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
  - Canada
    - Image #51348 Champlain statue, Quebec 1901 [Canada], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51349 Wolfe and Montcalm Monument, Quebec 1901 [Canada], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51358 Str. Toronto, St. Lawrence River, 1901 [Canada], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51368 Champlain Street, Quebec [Canada], 3.5x7 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous/unidentified
    - Image #1 Alpine Pass, 4.5x6.5 (Box 1)
    - Image #51128 Michigan, the lighthouse, Palmer Peak, Detroit, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51206 Birth of a century: Plate 85, Woman at the matate, Moki Pueblos, 1895, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51210 Bringing in the harvest, Moki Pueblos, ca. 1902, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51211 A Chinese maiden, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51228 Dogwood blossoms, 3.5x7 (Box 1)
    - Image #51271 Old house at Far Hills, N.J. [New Jersey], 3.5x7 (Box 1)